<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>python on Jack Baker</title>
    <link>http://jackcbaker.github.io/tags/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in python on Jack Baker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 13:17:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://jackcbaker.github.io/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Upweighting your recent observations in regression and classification</title>
      <link>http://jackcbaker.github.io/posts/upweight-recent-observations-regression-classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 13:17:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jackcbaker.github.io/posts/upweight-recent-observations-regression-classification/</guid>
      <description>COVID-19 has changed many established patterns. We&amp;rsquo;re all having to adjust to a new normal: how do we get our data science models to adjust as well?
COVID aside, in any regression or classification problem where observations have a time element, old patterns can become stale. For this reason, I&amp;rsquo;m often asking myself &amp;ndash; how do I upweight my most recent observations? In this post I explain how to do this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A python equivalent for R markdown</title>
      <link>http://jackcbaker.github.io/posts/python-equivalent-rmarkdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 20:20:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jackcbaker.github.io/posts/python-equivalent-rmarkdown/</guid>
      <description>R markdown is a powerful tool for sharing insights with stakeholders. You can write snippets of R code that generate plots. This can then be compiled to a HTML or pdf file that you can share with non-technical stakeholders.
This is not as straightforward in python. Yes, Jupyter notebooks are a great way of sharing analysis with other developers. But compiling to HTML/pdf, with code snippets removed, that looks nice enough for a non-technical stakeholder, I&amp;rsquo;ve found clunky using Jupyter notebooks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to include libraries in your project while also editing them</title>
      <link>http://jackcbaker.github.io/posts/include-libraries-project-editing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 18:29:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jackcbaker.github.io/posts/include-libraries-project-editing/</guid>
      <description>I came across this issue the other day: I wanted to include a library in a project, but to make it work in my code I would have to edit it. I then needed to write those changes back to the original library, with minimal faff. This post explains the best way I found of doing this.
An obvious solution is to include the whole codebase of the library into your project.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
